# **Ricardo Andres Diaz Rincon**

## **Summary**

I'm a full-stack developer. I graduated with Honors in Computer Systems Engineering from the Universidad del Valle in Cali, Colombia. During my time at this institution, I was a Research Assistant at the CAMALEON Research Group. My research has focused on Natural Language Processing, Brain-Computer Interfaces, EEG Signal Processing, Computational Neuroscience, Human-Computer Interaction, and Artificial Intelligence. My previous work, which aimed to create Music and Generative Art from brain activity, has been presented at the University of Brasilia and the Etruscan Museum in Rome.

### **Scientific Interests**

I am interested in the intersection between science and art. This is why I have tried different approaches whose goal is to depict human beings' uniqueness by means of their brain activity, allowing users to create different art pieces without them being artists. My scientific interests also focus on Natural Language Processing and improving the life quality of human beings through BCI devices and novel computational techniques. This involves Deep Learning for EEG signals, speech decoding from neural activity (Speech impairment), spinal cord injury and stroke rehabilitation, neuroprosthetics and Brain-Art therapy in the treatment of patients with dementia.

## **Professional Experience**

Full-Stack Developer 10/2020 – Present

Scientific Colombia Program, Universidad del Rosario

• Developing economical experiments in Django to characterize the behavior of informal social-economic agents in Colombia.

Full-Stack Developer 02/2019 - 07/2020

Vice-Rectory of Research, Universidad del Valle

• Implementation and design of a web-based interactive game that allows teaching Colombian History to children in visual diversity.

Full-Stack Developer 06/2018 – 12/2018 CINARA Institute, Universidad del Valle

• Implementation and design of the Agua Conference website.

Computer Repair Services 02/2011 - 07/2015 Shekina Cybercafé

• Computer hardware repairing/maintenance.

# **Research Experience**

**Deep Learning Research Engineer** 04/2019 – Present

**Ed Kravitz Lab**, Harvard Medical School

- Collaboration with Dr. Caroline Palavicino-Maggio. Training and developing deep learning algorithms that will enable the study of multi-dimensional phenotypic differences in social behavior for significantly improved quantification and analysis of aggression in female Drosophila (fruit fly).
- Using DeepLabCut and Residual Neural Networks (ResNet) for multianimal pose estimation.

**Research Assistant** 02/2018 – 07/2020

**CAMALEON Research Group**, Universidad del Valle

- Data Analysis.
- Programming.
- Encephalographic Signals Processing.
- Collaboration with faculty to develop publications.

# **Teaching Experience**

- **Teaching Assistant.** Linear Algebra. Fall, Summer, Spring 2018.
- Teaching Assistant. Linear Algebra. Fall, Spring 2017.
- **Teaching Assistant.** Mathematics. Summer 2017.
- Teaching Assistant. Linear Algebra. Spring 2017.
- **Teaching Assistant.** Linear Algebra. Fall, Spring 2016.

## Contact

- ricardoandres.propio@gmail.com
- (S) Google Scholar
- ResearchGate
- in LinkedIn
- ORCID ID
- GitHub Profile
- Website

## **Technical Skills**

#### Back-End

Python: ★★★★
Django: ★★★★
Node.js: ★★★☆
PHP: ★★★☆
C++: ★★★☆
C#: ★★★☆☆

### Front-End

Tailwind CSS: ★★★★
Bootstrap: ★★★★
React.js: ★★★★
Vue.js: ★★★★
P5.js: ★★★☆

HTML5/CSS3: ★★★★★

#### Deployment

Heroku: ★★★★
AWS: ★★★☆
Firebase: ★★★☆☆

#### **Databases**

PostgreSQL: ★★★★MongoDB: ★★★★

### **Education**

**BSc. Computer Systems Engineering** 02/2015 – 08/2020

Universidad del Valle, Cali (Colombia).

Thesis with **Summa Cum Laude Distinction**.

## **Bootcamps**

**Online Summer School Student 07/2020** 

### **Neuromatch Academy.**

Computational Neuroscience Summer School covering:

Modelling, Statistical Analysis, Dimensionality Reduction, Bayesian Statistics, Linear Systems, Decision Making, Optimal Control, Reinforcement Learning, Neurons Modeling, Dynamic Networks, Deep Learning.

#### Courses

2020. Coursera. Introduction to HTML5.

2014. Coursera. Programming for Everybody (Python).

## **Journal Papers**

**2020. Diaz Rincon, R. A.** Towards Brain Computer Interfaces and Generative Art. GASATHJ (Generative Art Science and Technology Hard Journal). <a href="https://www.gasathj.com/tiki-read\_article.php?articleId=76">https://www.gasathj.com/tiki-read\_article.php?articleId=76</a>.

**2019. Diaz Rincon, R. A.**, Reyes Vera, J. M., & Rodriguez C, P. J. Generando música a través de la Actividad Cerebral. Brazilian Journal of Development, 5(6), 5375–5388. <a href="https://doi.org/10.34117/bjdv5n6-077">https://doi.org/10.34117/bjdv5n6-077</a>.

## **Conference Papers**

**2019. Diaz Rincon, R. A.**, Reyes Vera, J. M., & Rodriguez C, P. J. An approach to Generative Art from Brain Computer Interfaces. In Celestino Soddu (Ed.), XXII Generative Art Conference - GA2019 (pp. 332–343). Retrieved from http://www.generativeart.com/GA2019\_web/50\_RicardoDiaz\_168x240.pdf.

**2018. Diaz Rincon, R. A.**, Reyes Vera, J. M., & Rodriguez C, P. J. Generando música a través de la Actividad Cerebral. Nuevas Ideas en Informática Educativa, 14, 600–605. http://www.tise.cl/Volumen14/TISE2018/600.pdf.

### **Conference Presentations**

**2019**. XXII Generative Art Conference. Etruscan National Museum of Villa Giulia. Rome, Italy. <u>An Approach to Generative Art from Brain Computer Interfaces.</u>

**2018**. TISE 2018. University of Brasilia. Brasilia, Brazil. <u>Generando música a</u> partir de la actividad cerebral.

#### **Committees**

**2018 - Present.** Brazilian Journal of Development. Editorial Board. <a href="https://www.brazilianjournals.com/index.php/BRJD/about/editorialTeam">https://www.brazilianjournals.com/index.php/BRJD/about/editorialTeam</a>

### **Invited Talks**

2020. Otree Crash course (In Spanish).

Videos: https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1YHBW26fQ-

C2ULEmz3HH5J8wbGPkyqdxv?usp=sharing

GitHub Repository: https://github.com/Ricardo0621/otree-workshop

**2020.** Introduction to Brain Computer Interfaces. Universidad del Valle (In Spanish). https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RhW\_uWIKyZQ

**2020.** Generating music and generative art from Brain Computer Interfaces. Universidad del Valle (In Spanish).

**2019.** What are BCI devices and what can we do with them? Universidad del Valle (In Spanish).

# **Media Coverage**

**2021.** Thoughts on how to create more supportive, equitable, and engaging environments in Academia. <a href="https://werepstem.com/2021/02/08/supporting-black-scientists-year-round/">https://werepstem.com/2021/02/08/supporting-black-scientists-year-round/</a>

# **Language Certifications**

**2021.** EF SET English Certificate 79/100 (C2 Proficient). https://www.efset.org/cert/LDyM2X

# Languages

Spanish (Native):  $\star\star\star\star\star$ English (Fluent):  $\star\star\star\star\star$ Portuguese (Proficient):  $\star\star\star\star\star$ German (Intermediate):  $\star\star\star\star\star$ 

# **Managerial Skills**

Team Leadership:  $\star\star\star\star$ UI/UX Enhancement:  $\star\star\star\star$ Agile Methodology:  $\star\star\star\star$